Register of the William Henry Hastings papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Henry Hastings papers
1942-1945
70007
Hastings, William Henry.
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Materials relate to the Japanese invasion and occupation of the Philippines and the Japanese prison camp at Santo Tomás. The papers include scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and correspondence, newspaper clippings files, a typescript of letters and diary entries describing time spent in the camps, and a roster of prisoners of the Santo Tomás internment camp.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1970.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
An American merchant seaman, Hastings lived in Japanese-occupied Philippines during World War II. He was interned by the Japanese at the Santo Tomás internment center in Manila and at the Los Baños (or Sulphur Springs) center from January 8, 1942, until he was repatriated on the S.S. Jean Lafitte, February 22, 1945, arriving in San Francisco on March 30, 1945.
Scope and Content of Collection
Materials relate to the events of the Japanese invasion and occupation of the Philippines, Japanese prison camps at Santo Tomás and Los Baños (or Sulphur Springs) in the Philippines. The papers include scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and correspondence, newspaper clippings files, a typescript of letters and diary entries describing time spent in the camps, and a roster of prisoners of the Santo Tomás internment camp.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Santo Tomas Internment Camp (Manila, Philippines); Prisoners of war.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps.; Concentration camps--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.
Collection Contents
- Scrapbooks and news clippings, 1942-1944. (Folder 1-5)
  Generally consists of news clippings describing the events of the Japanese invasion and occupation of the Philippines, as reported in local papers. Later scrapbooks also include other materials such as correspondence. The series also includes files of clippings, mostly dating from 1944, assumed to be collected materials meant to be pasted into a scrapbook. Arranged by format, then chronologically.
  - Scrapbooks, January 1942-July 1943 (Folder 1-4)
    - January 1 - February 3, 1942 (Folder 1: 1)
    - February 6 - March 15, 1942 (Folder 1: 2)
    - March 16 - April 15, 1942 (Folder 1: 3)
    - April 15 - May 7, 1942 (Folder 1: 4)
    - May 8 - June 2, 1942 (Folder 1: 5)
    - June 3 - June 29, 1942 (Folder 1: 6)
    - June 30 - July 31, 1942 (Folder 1: 7)
    - August 1 - August 24, 1942 (Folder 1: 8)
    - August 25 - September 20, 1942 (Folder 2: 1)
    - September 21 - October 13, 1942 (Folder 2: 2)
    - October 14 - October 28, 1942 (Folder 2: 3)
    - October 28 - November 17, 1942 (Folder 2: 4)
    - October 30 - November 30, 1942 (Folder 2: 5)
    - November 13 - November 29, 1942 (Folder 2: 6)
    - November 29 - December 13, 1942 (Folder 2: 7)
    - December 14 - December 31, 1942 (Folder 2: 8)
    - November 19, 1942 - January 15, 1943 (Folder 3: 1)
    - January 1 - January 16, 1943 (Folder 3: 2)
    - January 15 - January 29, 1943 (Folder 3: 3)
    - January 27 - February 13, 1943 (Folder 3: 4)
    - January 17 - April 14, 1943 (Folder 3: 5)
    - February 9 - February 28, 1943 (Folder 3: 6)
    - March 1 - March 26, 1943 (Folder 3: 7)
    - March 29 - April 21, 1943 (Folder 3: 8)
    - April 15 - July 10, 1943 (Folder 4: 1)
    - April 22 - May 6, 1943 (Folder 4: 2)
    - May 6 - May 25, 1943 (Folder 4: 3)
    - May 17 - June 22, 1943 (Folder 4: 4)
    - September 30 - October 28, 1942 (Folder 4: 5)
    - July 11 - October 3, 1943 (Folder 4: 6)
    - July 1 - July 29, 1943 (Folder 4: 7)
    - June 16 - July 2, 1943 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1942-1944 (Folder 5: 1-3)
- Internment camp materials, 1942-1945. (Folder 5)
  Includes a roster of individuals in the Santo Tomás internment camp, a typescript of letters and diary entries describing time spent in the camps, a list of Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Ribbon awardees, and a nautical map of San Francisco, where Hastings returned after the war. Arranged by format.
  - Santo Tomás Camp roster, 1945 (Folder 5: 4-5)
  - "Internment to Me" typescript of letters and diary entries describing time spent in the camps, 1942-1944 (Folder 5: 6-8)
  - Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Ribbon awardees list, including Hastings, 1 May 1945 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Nautical map of San Francisco, 1943 (Folder 5: 10)